RICARDO CISTERNA SANTOS

PROFILE

IT Consultant, focused on product development. With experience in web systems development, desktop software and microcontrollers firmware. Also with experience leading multidisciplinary teams (with developers, designers, electronic engineers, speech therapists, among others), analyzing data in different contexts and implementing machine learning algorithms.

EXPERIENCE

SENIOR FULLSTACK ENGINEER, WANDERJAUNT (THROUGH TERMINAL) - 05/2022 - 06/2022

Senior software engineer at the engineering team. Major activities:

- Helped to migrate the backend API and frontend views from REST API to GraphQL API.
- Helped to migrate the business logic in a new implementation of the financial models.

Contact: Barrett Glasauer, CTO. +1 408-393-6155.

Technologies: Python 3.9+ (Django, DRF, , Celery), JS (Node 16+, Vue.js 2+), Git.

BACKEND ENGINEER, CORNERSHOP BY UBER - 11/2021 - 04/2022

Software engineer focused on the backend in the company's global Finance vertical. Major activities:

- Refactor the billing logic implementation for all chilean orders.
- Define and document the specifications and development plan for the automatization of the Brazilian partners billing process.

Contact: Thomas Maureira, Engineering Manager. +56 9 7184 8641.

Technologies: Python 3.8+ (Django, DRF, Celery), Metabase, Git.

PRODUCT LEAD, CONTINUUM - 12/2019-11/2021

Product leader and consultant on the company's Healthcare vertical. Major activities:

- Team leader in charge of designing and implementing the telemedicine platform for Clínica Alemana de Santiago.
- Support and continuous improvement consultant for Transbank services (payment gateway).
- Implementation of RESTful services in AWS lambda.
- Design and implementation of a web scraping robot for the chilean Internal Tax Service.

Contact: Liliana Reyes, CTO. +56 9 7669 1128.

Technologies: Python 3.6+ (selenium, beautifulsoup), Javascript (node 12+), Git.

SOFTWARE ENGINEER, CADETECH - 04/2018-10/2019

In charge of design, develop and implement IT solutions for the company's Industrial Applications division. Major activities:

- Implementation of clasificación algorithms (machine learning) for data analysis.
- Design and implementation of RESTful APIs for storage information from microcontrollers installed on site.
- Design and implementation of firmware for microcontrollers.

Contact: Rodolfo Köck, Division Manager. +56 9 9883 8553.

Technologies: Python 2.7/3.6+ (SciKit Learn, Django, DRF), C++ (arduino), Git, Debian 9.

SOFTWARE ENGINEER, TEKNIP - 06/2015-04/2018

Software developer for time-critical cutting optimization software, used for automatic handling of timber machine. Also, in charge of on-site installation and commissioning, and for customer communication.

Contact: Robinson Hernandez, Head of IT Department. +56 9 4220 8454.

Technologies: C# (WPF, .NET Framework 4.7.x), SQL Server, Git, Windows 8.1/10

SOFTWARE ENGINEER (FREELANCE), CEDIT - 11/2016-11/2017

Freelance developer of personnel administration and control system, dynamic access permission and stock management, for Biotechnology Center of Universidad de Concepción.

Contact: Rodrigo Venegas, Co-Founder. +56 9 9087 1921.

Technologies: PHP (Laravel PHP Framework 5.3), Semantic UI, PostgreSQL, Git.

SOFTWARE ENGINEER (FREELANCE), DINAMAKER - 06/2015-11/2015

Freelance developer of a system for organization and planning of personnel training and accidents, for Celulosa Arauco y Constitución..

Contact: Miguel Chandía, Founder. +56 9 5511 6860.

Technologies: PHP (Laravel PHP Framework 5.1), Semantic UI, PostgreSQL, Git.

DEVELOPER, INDEPENDENT PROJECT - 12/2013-05/2015

Developer of voice phonetic analysis software, with real-time visualization of results (oscillogram, spectrogram, among others), in the context of the project "Voice phonetic analysis", awarded in a public contest of Innova Bio-Bio.

Technologies: Python (ScyPy, NumPy, PyQTGraph), Git, GNU/Linux.

FORMAL EDUCATION

UNIVERSIDAD DEL BIO-BIO - INFORMATICS ENGINEERING, 2010-2014

SKILLS

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming Languages: Python (3.6+), C++ (c++11),

C# (5.x/6.x), PHP (5.x, 7.x, 8.x), Javascript (EC6). **Databases**: PostgreSQL, SQL Server, MySQL, DynamoDB.

Operative systems: MS Windows 8.1+, Mac OS X, GNU/

Linux (Debian/Archlinux).

Others: Git SCM, Docker, Bash/ZSH.

SOFT SKILLS

Main: Ethical, problem solver,

sociable, team player.

Others: Responsible, creative,

confident.

LANGUAGES

- Spanish: native

- English: C1 (certified by Poliglota)

AREAS OF INTEREST

- Artificial Inteligence.
- Software for applied sciences.